（スレイ）ライラ 竜巻の中に…
Lailah! There's something inside the tornado!
Oh, no...
（ライラ）そんな
（ミクリオ）まさか
It can't be...
ドラゴンだ
A dragon!
（ミクリオ）動いた
It's on the move!
Alisha! Alisha!
（マルトラン）
アリーシャ アリーシャ！
アリーシャ こっちへ来るぞ
Alisha, it's coming this way!
Guards! Where are the guards?!
衛兵… 衛兵はおらぬか
It's heading toward the palace!
（ミクリオ）王宮に向かっている
Alisha!
アリーシャ…
We'll ride upon the wind to follow
Your path leading far off into the distance
The answers we seek won't be easy to find
We set out knowing that from the start
We wander endlessly to leave behind records of our dream
It's worth it if it widens our map of the world
Resound, O song of the wind
Should we forgo sight, the voices of our hearts will push us forward
We aim always ever higher
Carry, O song of the wind
Should we go without hearing, the voices of our hearts will stream forth
Emitting a dazzling radiance
Your azure melody rings true
Allow anyone seeking shelter into the palace!
王宮に
避難してくる者がいたら
中へ入れよ
よいな？
（兵士たち）はっ
Understood?
Yes, ma'am!
ん？ あれは…
What is that?
Sorey!
スレイ
It's too dangerous!
（ライラ）危険です
So, do you have a plan?
（ミクリオ）
スレイ 何か手があるのか？
No, not really, but I can't just...
（スレイ）分からない…
分からないよ だけど…
Sorey...
スレイ…
Are we in the clear?
助かったのか？
（ミクリオ）破滅と死をもたらす
不吉の象徴 ドラゴン
The dragon is a symbol of ill omen that begets death and destruction.
ねえ ライラ あのドラゴンも
穢(けが)れによるものなのか？
Hey, Lailah, is that dragon also a manifestation of malevolence?
ええ おそらく
Most likely, yes.
いまだに この目が信じられません
I can hardly believe my eyes, though.
A dragon actually appeared.
まさかドラゴンが
本当に現れるなんて
Sorey!
（アリーシャ）スレイ！
（スレイ）あっ… アリーシャ
Alisha!
Thank you for saving Ladylake!
ありがとう
レディレイクを救ってくれて
あ… いやあ… 俺は…
No, I didn't do...
Sorey, look!
スレイ 見てみなよ
The dragon disappeared!
It's the Shepherd!
Master Shepherd! Master Shepherd!
（一同）導師様！ 導師様！
The Shepherd!
Wait! Calm down, please!
（スレイ）待ってくれ
あ… 落ち着いて 頼むから
Oh, Shepherd!
（バルトロ）おお 導師殿
ありがとうございます
Thank you!
あのドラゴン 導師殿のお力で
食い止めていただいたのですな
You stopped that dragon with your powers, didn't you?
I didn't do anything.
（スレイ）俺は何もやってないよ
（バルトロ）
オホホ ご謙遜をなさる
Such modesty.
導師殿 １つお願いがございます
（アリーシャ）ん…
Shepherd, I have a request to ask of you.
（バルトロ）
感謝のしるしとしまして―
As a token of our appreciation, won't you join us for dinner?
食事にお招きしたいのですが
お受けいただけますか？
What do you say?
バルトロ卿 どういうつもりだ？
Lord Bartlow, what are you up to?
Why, it's just common courtesy.
さて どうと言われますと…
What's so strange about offering the
Shepherd dinner for his valiant efforts?
私は ただ
導師殿に少しでも―
疲れを取っていただければと
思っているしだい
Very well. I accept your offer.
分かった 伺うよ
（バルトロ）オホホ 導師殿が
招きに応じてくださったぞ
The Shepherd has accepted my invitation!
スレイ…
Sorey...
アリーシャも一緒に来てくれる？
Will you come too?
I'm sorry. Can you stop for a bit?
ごめん ちょっと止めて
ライラ
（ライラ）はい
Lailah...
Yes...
Malevolence hasn't consumed Ladylake yet, but there's not much time.
（ライラ）レディレイクは
まだ穢れきっていませんが―
それほど時間は残されていない
そう思いますわ
That's the feeling I get.
（スレイ）何とかしなきゃ
We have to do something.
（側近）
ようこそおいでくださいました
Welcome!
（側近）ああ アリーシャ様は
どうぞ そのままで
Please stay right there, Princess Alisha.
お送りいたします
I will escort you.
Escort?
送る？
I have a message from His Majesty the King...
（側近）国王陛下から
お言葉を賜っております
"Come immediately to the palace."
“急ぎ王宮に来られたし”と
No one told me—
そのような話… あ…
（側近）陛下が―
His Majesty awaits.
お待ちでございます
アリーシャさんには
同席してもらいたくないようですわ
It seems they don't want Alisha's presence.
スレイ すまないが…
Forgive me, Sorey, but...
I'll be fine.
俺なら大丈夫だよ
では 導師様
Master Shepherd...
（バルトロ）ようこそ 導師殿
Welcome, Shepherd.
Hello.
（スレイ）こんにちは
導師殿は アリーシャ姫と
どのようなご関係か？
What is your relation with Lady Alisha, if I may ask?
We're just friends.
友達だよ
友達…
Friends?
We haven't known each other for very long,
but I consider her a good friend.
そんなに会ってから
長くはないけど―
いい友達だと思ってる
（バルトロ）ほう
私とも友達になってくれるかね？
I see. Can we be friends too?
You want to be friends?
（スレイ）俺と友達になりたいの？
Yes.
（バルトロ）うむ
（スレイ）そうは見えないけど
That's not the impression I get.
（バルトロ）ん… 乾杯としようか
Here's a toast.
（ミクリオ）スレイ
うかつに飲まないほうがいい
Sorey...
Don't blindly accept everything they give you.
It's pretty good.
うまい
ほんとだ おいしい
Yeah, this tastes good.
Is it to your liking? It's the pride of Hyland.
（バルトロ）お口に合いましたかな
ハイランドの名産です
But with the recent disasters,
I'm afraid the harvest has suffered.
ただ昨今は 災害続きで
収穫が芳しくはありませんが
Why did you want to see me?
（スレイ）話って何？
What do you plan to do now?
（バルトロ）導師殿は
このあと どうされるおつもりか
私どもとしましては
ぜひとも導師殿のお力を―
We believe it would be for the best if the Shepherd were to lend us his strength.
お借りできればと
考えているのですが
I'm sorry. I have other plans.
（スレイ）
ごめん もう決めてあるんだ
（バルトロ）ん？
お聞かせいただいてよろしいか？
May I ask what they are?
I'm gonna go after the dragon.
ドラゴンを追ってみようと思う
Go after? And then what?
追って…
どうなさるおつもりか？
I don't know what I can do, but...
自分に何ができるのか
分からないけど―
ドラゴンが不吉の象徴なら
そこにこそ―
If a dragon is a symbol of ill omen,
perhaps therein lies the key to fixing the world.
世界をよくする手がかりが
あるかもしれない
Sorey...
（ライラ）スレイさん
Alisha!
（スレイ）アリーシャ
（アリーシャ）ん？
There you are.
（スレイ）ここにいたの？
（アリーシャ）フッ…
（アリーシャ）日が暮れる
今日は ここまでだな
The sun is setting. I guess we'll call it a day.
Sorey, I'm being sent to Marlind.
スレイ 私は
マーリンドへ行くことになった
It's a direct order from His Majesty.
国王陛下からの勅命だ
Does that Bartlow guy have anything to do with this?
それって
あのバルトロって人のせいなのか？
I don't know, but even if he does...
（アリーシャ）分からない
しかし そうだとしても―
It doesn't change the fact that Marlind is suffering from an epidemic.
疫病で苦しんでいる人たちを
放っておくことはできない
（側近）よろしかったのですか？
導師をあのまま帰らせて
Was it wise to let the Shepherd leave like that?
レディレイクを
出ていくのであれば―
If he's leaving Ladylake, there won't be any bloodshed here.
今 この場で
血を流すこともあるまい
Then what about the war preparations?
では 戦の準備は？
We proceed as planned, of course.
無論 進めてくれ
Lailah, can we talk?
（ミクリオ）
ライラ 少しいいかい？
What's wrong, Mikleo?
（ライラ）
どうしたのですか？ ミクリオさん
I was watching Sorey today, and it got me thinking.
今日 スレイを見てて思ったんだ
スレイは導師となって―
Since becoming a Shepherd, Sorey's been facing his destiny head-on.
その運命から目を背けずに
前進しているって
遠い存在になったと
思っていらっしゃるのですか？
Do you feel like he's climbing out of your reach?
I don't know. Maybe.
どうだろう 分からないな
では 今後どうしたいか
ミクリオさんのお考えは？
So what would you like to do from now on?
I don't know that either.
それも分からない
分からないけど―
But even so...
I know we can't stay like this forever.
今のままの関係では
いられないって思ってる
That's right.
スレイは導師になった
Sorey has become a Shepherd, so what am I supposed to do?
なら僕は 何をするべきなのか
しばらくスレイと旅をするつもりで
故郷を出てきたんだけど
I left home with the idea of traveling with him.
Will you return to Elysia?
イズチにお戻りになる？
（ミクリオ）いや
一瞬 そう考えもしたけど―
No, although that thought has crossed my mind.
If Sorey's going to travel the world as the Shepherd,
スレイが今後―
導師として世界を巡ることに
なるんだとしたら―
I can't just let him go alone.
放ってはおけないと思ってね
You really love Sorey, don't you, Mikleo?
（ライラ）ミクリオさんは―
本当にスレイさんのことが
お好きなんですね
（ミクリオ）腐れ縁なだけさ
We're stuck with each other.
You want to know what you can do for Sorey?
（ライラ）ミクリオさんが
スレイさんにしてあげられること
もちろん ありますわ
I might have just the thing.
Lailah, we have to go after Mikleo right away!
（スレイ）ライラ
すぐにミクリオの後を追おう
What if a hellion appears? He can't handle it alone!
憑魔(ひょうま)が現れたら
１人でどうする気だよ
うう… そのくらい
分かってるはずなのに
He should know that by now!
どうして１人で…
Why'd he go alone?!
１人で行くだけの理由が―
I guess he must've had his reasons for going alone.
ミクリオには
あったってことだよな
Are you sure you don't have to go after him?
追いかけなくても
よろしいんですか？
Yeah.
俺にも ほんとの導師になるために
やることがある
I have things to do if I'm to become a real Shepherd.
If you leave the town of Ladylake and keep heading north, you'll come to a huge lake.
（ライラ）
レディレイクの街を出て―
北へ 北へと
どこまでも進んでいきますと―
大きな湖に たどりつきますわ
そこに ガラハドと呼ばれる
遺跡がありますの
There you'll find the Galahad Ruins.
その遺跡には 魔を鎮める
伝説の神器が眠っているのです
Inside the ruins is an armatus that can suppress evil spirits.
An armatus?
（ミクリオ）神器？
（ライラ）はい
私にとっての聖剣と同じもの
It's like what the Sacred Blade is to me.
聖遺物ですわ
A sacred relic.
（ライラ）ミクリオさんが
それを手にできれば…
If you are able to obtain it...
スレイに 僕なりの助力ができる
I will acquire the power to assist Sorey.
（ライラ）そう思いますわ
I believe so.
You're leaving now?
（スレイ）行くんだね
（アリーシャ）んっ
Oh, Sorey!
あっ スレイ
病の進行は
待ってはくれないからな
The plague waits for no one.
Here, Alisha.
アリーシャ これを
This is...
（アリーシャ）これは…
（スレイ）
返すの 遅くなってごめん
I'm sorry. I meant to return it sooner.
Mikleo found it in the ruins.
ミクリオが
遺跡から拾ってきてくれたんだ
ありがとう 本当にうれしい
大切なものなんだ
Thank you so much!
Words can't express my gratitude.
It's very precious to me.
Sorey, if you're able, would you be willing to escort us for a bit?
スレイ もし可能なら
途中まででもいい
Even just part of the way?
我々の護衛に
来てはもらえないだろうか
もちろん
Sure thing!
For the first time, the people have seen a dragon.
（アリーシャ）初めて皆が
ドラゴンという存在を―
目の当たりにした
A creature that crossed the veil of legends, into reality.
伝説が そのベールを脱いで
現実のものになったんだ
（スレイ）その伝説に手がかりが？
So the legend holds clues?
Yes. Have you heard of Rayfalke Spiritcrest?
（アリーシャ）
そう 霊峰レイフォルク
It's mentioned often in dragon folklore.
ドラゴンの伝承に
度々 登場する―
ほとんど人が出入りしない険しい山
A dangerously high mountain where people rarely go.
（スレイ）分かった 行ってみるよ
All right, then that's where I'll go.
They're called trangelongs and are found only in these woods.
トレンジロングスだ
この森だけに住む
Are they dangerous?
危なくないの？
大丈夫 おとなしい生き物だよ
Don't worry. They're gentle creatures.
へえ
Damn, what kind of hellion is it?
クソッ 何の憑魔だ？
ヘビか？ トカゲか？
A snake? Or lizard?
ハァ…
Eat as much as you'd like.
（アリーシャ）
遠慮せずに食べてくれ
Thanks.
ありがとう
What about Lailah? Does she truly not need to eat?
ライラ様は 本当に
召し上がらなくても大丈夫なのか？
（スレイ）お気遣いなくって
She says not to worry.
Then have something to drink, at least.
（アリーシャ）
では 飲み物だけでも
すぐそこに果実がなっていたのでな
I found some ripe fruits nearby.
それをすりおろして
湯で溶いたものだ
I grated them and added hot water.
んん！
（スレイ）すっぱ～ でも…
It's so sour! But wait...
だろ？
See?
うん おいしい
Yeah, this is great!
Sorey...
（ライラ）スレイさん
Alisha, are you ready?
アリーシャ いい？
（アリーシャ）ん？
Alisha?
アリーシャさん
Lailah!
ライラ様
Thank you, Alisha.
ありがとう アリーシャさん
（アリーシャ）あっ いえ…
Don't mention it.
（修道士）ぐはっ うう…
（修道士）ぐはっ！
Trangelongs never attack humans!
トレンジロングスが
人を襲うなんて
Sorey...
（ライラ）スレイさん
（スレイ）ああ あれは…
I know. That's...
（修道士）ぐわあ！
a hellion!
（スレイ）憑魔だ
After we pass two more towns and cross a large river, we'll arrive at Marlind.
（アリーシャ）あと村を２つ通って
大きな川を渡ったらマーリンドだ
（スレイ）
そこは どういう所なの？
What's Marlind like?
（アリーシャ）人口は
レディレイクの次に多く―
It's the most populated city after Ladylake and serves as the secondary capital.
副首都でもあるんだ
文化的水準も高く
識字率も国で一番を誇る
It's a very cultured city with the
highest literacy rate in the nation.
父も自慢の街だった
It used to be my father's pride.
（スレイ）だった？
Used to?
Are the effects of the epidemic that bad?
疫病の影響は そんなにひどいの？
I'm not certain how much we can do by taking a group of doctors there.
医師団が行っても―
その効果は
どの程度 期待できるか…
Can I ask about you, Sorey?
スレイのこと 聞いていいか？
Sure.
（スレイ）もちろん
（アリーシャ）イズチから
出たことがないと以前 聞いたが
You told me once that you had never left Elysia.
Yeah.
俺が まだ赤ん坊だった頃に
大火事があって―
When I was just a baby, there was a great fire.
And Gramps saved me from it.
そこをジイジが
助けてくれたらしいんだけど―
I've lived in Elysia ever since.
それからは
ずっとイズチの中で暮らしてたよ
I wasn't able to talk to him,
but he must be a great man.
私は話すことができなかったが
素晴らしい方なのだろうな
（スレイ）まあね 俺たちは
ジイジの加護に守られてた
I guess. We were all protected by his blessing.
下界に来て それがよく分かったよ
I know how important that is now that I'm out here.
スレイは その…
Sorey, you're...
You're human, right?
人間なのだよな？
（スレイ）もちろん
Of course!
その… 見えていたのか？
最初から天族のこと
So were you always able to see seraphim?
Now that you mention it...
そう言われると…
見えてたんじゃないかな
I guess I have.
ジイジは共に暮らしたことで―
Gramps said I learned to see them by living with them.
天族の存在を
捉えたって言ってたけど
天族のことを もっと知りたい
教えてもらっていいだろうか？
I want to know more about seraphim.
Will you teach me?
It says in the Celestial Record,
「天遺(てんい)見聞録」にも
“太古の時代―”
"In ancient times, people could see and hear the seraphim and coexisted with them."
“人は 天族を知覚し
共に暮らしていた”ってあるよね
Seraphim existed in towns and villages, as earth in the land,
天族は それぞれの街にいて―
土として大地を 風として空を
as wind in the sky, water in the rivers,
水として川を 火として生活を
fire in the hearths, protecting the balance of life.
その均衡を保っていた
（アリーシャ）土 風 水 火
Earth, wind, water, fire...
Yeah. Seraphim aren't omnipotent either.
They have their strengths and weaknesses.
（スレイ）そう
天族も万能じゃないから―
得意 不得意はあるんだ
Lailah is a fire seraph, and Mikleo excels at controlling water.
ライラは火の天族だし―
ミクリオは
水を操ることにたけている
（アリーシャ）なのに―
But we are no longer able to see and hear the seraphim.
私たちは天族を
知覚できなくなってしまった
Why?
なぜ？
（スレイ）うん…
だからなのか？
この災厄の時代が生まれたのは
Is that why this age of calamity was born?
（スレイ）
人は天族を尊ぶ気持ちをなくし―
Man lost their reverence for seraphim.
疑いや邪念 争いの心を
強く持ってしまった
Their hearts became consumed with suspicion, wickedness, and conflict.
ジイジには そう聞いた
That's what Gramps told me.
しかし それなら災厄は―
Then...
Does that mean humans are the cause of calamities?
人の心が生んだものだということに
なるのだろうか
I don't know.
（スレイ）分からない
ただ この世界に穢れが
満ちていることは事実だし―
But it's a fact that this world is overflowing with malevolence.
災厄が
さらに大きくなっていることも―
And there's no mistaking that the calamities are getting worse.
間違いないんじゃないかな
天族と人間が
一緒に暮らせる世界にしたい
You want to make a world where humans and seraphim can live together.
スレイは イズチで
そう言っていただろ？
That's what you said in Elysia.
Yeah.
Strange how I remember that so clearly.
不思議と鮮明に覚えているんだ
きっと スレイが幼い頃から―
You must believe that because you spent a long time living with seraphim.
天族と一緒に
暮らしてきたからなのだろうな
人ひとりで 寂しくもなく
You weren't lonely, even though you were the only human.
You're perfectly suited to be a Shepherd.
本当に 導師にふさわしい
（スレイ）そういえば―
That's true. I never felt lonely.
寂しいって思ったことって
なかったな
Because I had everyone.
みんながいてくれたから
ミクリオがいてくれたから
Because I had Mikleo.
If Lailah's right, the ruins should be around here.
ライラの言葉に
間違いがなければ―
この辺りに遺跡があるはずなんだが
I'm not gonna lose to you.
負けるわけにはいかないね
We're getting close.
近づいてきましたわね
That's Rayfalke.
あれがレイフォルク
行こう
Let's go.
I win again today, Sorey.
今日も僕の勝ちだね スレイ
I win today, Mikleo.
今日は俺の勝ちだ ミクリオ
The moon is beautiful tonight.
（ライラ）
今日の月は きれいですわね
どこかでミクリオさんも
見ていますわ
Somewhere, Mikleo is gazing at the same moon.
If we close our eyes now,
here on this journey with no turning back,
we can find our moments of peace
and make our wishes as we sleep
I dreamed of the world
and the hope and warmth
that our devotion can give to it
We can stop and rest
for the morrow
and together
we can laugh
I'm sure we can fulfill our duties
at the end
of this long journey
For now, let us sleep
and dream of the future
Let us walk together
Next Time
Why the long face, Lailah?
Sorey
Sorey, I've been thinking about purification.
Lailah
Oh. Purification is difficult.
Sorey
It is.
Lailah
I'm still new to being the Shepherd. To be honest, I'm not sure just how well I can purify this world.
Sorey
Sorey...
Lailah
But during my travels, I want to gain more power as a Shepherd to purify as much malevolence as possible in this world.
Sorey
So you were thinking about purification too!
Lailah
Well, I am the Shepherd, after all.
Sorey
...!
Lailah
What is it, Lailah?
Sorey
Ah, I got it!
Lailah
Huh? Got what?
Sorey
Purity, here I come!
Lailah
...?
Sorey
Sorey, you fight with Mikleo pure-itty much like a married couple! Purity, pretty, get it?
Lailah
So all this time you were trying to think of a pun?!
Sorey
Next time: "Rayfalke Spiritcrest."
Don't miss it!
Lailah
Lailah, who was that kid just now?
Sorey